<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Projects and Books on Looking for Wisdom</title>
    <link>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/projects/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Projects and Books on Looking for Wisdom</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 01 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/projects/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Dragon-Carving for Writers</title>
      <link>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/projects/dragon-carving/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/projects/dragon-carving/</guid>
      <description>At Looking for Wisdom, we are always interested in the cross-currents between literature and philosophy. For a long time, we&amp;rsquo;ve been particularly obsessed by the Medieval Chinese text, the Wenxin diaolong (文心雕龍) or The Carving of Dragons and the Literary Mind, written by a scholar called Liu Xie.&#xA;Liu was an interesting figure. He lived between the fifth and sixth centuries, and he brought together the philosophical thought of Daoist thinkers like Laozi and Zhuangzi, Confucians such as Mencius and (of course) Confucius himself, and the traditions of Buddhism.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hello, Stranger</title>
      <link>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/projects/hello-stranger/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 08 Jan 2022 08:01:35 +0300</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/projects/hello-stranger/</guid>
      <description>Hello, Stranger: Stories of Connections in a Divided World was published by Granta in 2021, when it was BBC Radio4 Book of the Week. It came out in paperback in 2022.&#xA;Reviews Humane and heart-warming&#xA;— Bookseller Editor’s Choice&#xA;An elegant and moving exploration of what it means to connect with strangers turns into an elegy for a much-missed way of life… while Hello, Stranger is a beautiful meditation on the pleasures and pains of a world to which many of us yearn to return, it may also be an elegy for a world that is lost to us for some time to come.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Finding Connections with the Premise Institute</title>
      <link>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/projects/premise-institute/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 02 Jan 2022 08:01:35 +0300</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/projects/premise-institute/</guid>
      <description>In February 2023, we&amp;rsquo;ll be running a session with the brilliant Premise Institute, exploring the question of how we can find connection in a divided world.&#xA;We love Premise&amp;rsquo;s work. They are based over in Portland, Oregon. We&amp;rsquo;ve never been over to Oregon, but we know its reputation as a mythical literary city, a place where everyone has their nose in a book. In this spirit, Premise run online sessions exploring books that raise beautiful questions, in a spirit of friendship and mutual enquiry.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Finding Our Sea-Legs</title>
      <link>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/projects/sea-legs/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 02 Jan 2022 08:01:35 +0300</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/projects/sea-legs/</guid>
      <description>Will Buckingham&amp;rsquo;s book Finding Our Sea-Legs: Ethics, Experience and the Ocean of Stories was first published by Kingston University Press in 2009. It&amp;rsquo;s a book about the power of storytelling, about how when it comes to ethics, often stories are the best chance we have of navigating the difficult seas that we face. It is less about finding a safe harbour, or alighting on ethical certainties, and more about managing to stay afloat, in the buffeting wind and tides.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Philosophy at the Chinbridge Institute</title>
      <link>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/projects/chinbridge-philosophy/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 02 Jan 2022 08:01:35 +0300</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/projects/chinbridge-philosophy/</guid>
      <description>In 2022, Looking for Wisdom&amp;rsquo;s Dr Will Buckingham worked with the Chinbridge Institute in Myanmar on developing and delivering two curricula as a part of the institute&amp;rsquo;s diploma in politics and governance.&#xA;The first curriculum was an introduction to philosophy, taking a truly global approach to the pursuit of wisdom. Chinram - the traditional homeland of the Chin peoples - is divided between Myanmar, Bangladesh and India, so we studied the philosophical traditions of India and China, two of Chinram&amp;rsquo;s largest neighbours, as well as the European tradition.</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
