<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Latest updates on Looking for Wisdom</title>
    <link>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/posts/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Latest updates on Looking for Wisdom</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 28 Jan 2024 00:16:46 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/posts/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Wansha Philosophy Salon</title>
      <link>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/wansha-philosophy-salon/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 28 Jan 2024 00:16:46 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/wansha-philosophy-salon/</guid>
      <description>My own philosophical education happened more or less by accident. In my twenties, I was a serious practitioner of Buddhism. I lived in a succession of Buddhist communities, working in temporary jobs, living on a shoestring, and spending my days writing and meditating. It was not financially sustainable in the long term, and the books I wrote at the time were all more or less unpublishable; but during these years of Buddhist practice, I had the luxury of having time to think.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Music is Joy</title>
      <link>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/music-joy/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Jan 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/music-joy/</guid>
      <description>On 21 January, we ran our first Wind&amp;amp;Bones public philosophy salon in Chinese, in collaboration with the Wansha Performing Arts Centre (涴莎藝術展演中心) in Tainan, Taiwan. We&amp;rsquo;re running these salons monthly, and we&amp;rsquo;re planning to publish an essay on the topic of the salon after each one. This is the first one, where we talked about philosophy and music.&#xA;A human universal Music is about as close to being a human universal as anything.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Looking for Wisdom in Taiwan</title>
      <link>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/in-taiwan/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 08 Sep 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/in-taiwan/</guid>
      <description>Here at Looking for Wisdom, 2023 has run away with us. No sooner had we set up the new site than we got involved in all kinds of other projects, and we had no choice but to put our work on the site temporarily to one side. Since we last posted, Hannah has had a short story collection accepted for publication and so is busy with endless edits, and Will has accepted a full-time job with Parami University in Myanmar, working online teaching philosophy and writing.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>7 Ways of Reading Philosophy: #6 Reading for laughs</title>
      <link>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/7-ways-06-for-laughs/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/7-ways-06-for-laughs/</guid>
      <description>When we moved the Looking for Wisdom HQ up to Scotland a year ago, we packed away all our philosophy books into boxes. There were a lot of boxes. So on the outside, with a big fat marker pen, we wrote the words: “Philosophy Books (warning: extremely heavy).” As jokes go, it was a pretty feeble one. But it kept us entertained through the stresses of the move.&#xA;This idea that philosophy is inherently and necessarily heavy is one that has a broad currency.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Kautilya on the Crooked Business of Politics</title>
      <link>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/kautilya/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Jan 2023 11:17:05 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/kautilya/</guid>
      <description>There is perhaps no headache greater than that of being a head of state. Or, in fact, being the head of anything. From the ancient world to the present day, it has been recognised that to be a ruler is to be condemned to a life of constant vigilance. You have to spend your days on the look-out for plots and enemies. You have to keep an eye on the unfolding power-plays within your court.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Looking for Wisdom: A New Look</title>
      <link>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/a-new-look/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/a-new-look/</guid>
      <description>Time for a Change It&amp;rsquo;s been two years since I started Looking for Wisdom, along with my Wind&amp;amp;Bones collaborator, Hannah Stevens. We set up the site when deep in the middle of Covid lockdown in Sofia, Bulgaria. We had time on our hands, the world seemed even more deeply puzzling than usual (as Aristotle points out in the Metaphysics, wonder or thaumazein is often a spur to philosophising), and we thought it would be fun to set up a philosophy newsletter.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Barbara Stok, on Comics and Cynics</title>
      <link>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/barbara-stok-hipparchia/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 16 Dec 2022 10:15:57 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/barbara-stok-hipparchia/</guid>
      <description>Looking for Wisdom Interview: Comics artist and writer Barbara Stok talks about dogs, Cynics, philosophers, and the art of living. Here at Looking for Wisdom, we’ve long been fascinated by the Cynic philosopher Hipparchia. So we were wildly excited when we stumbled across Dutch comic artist Barbara Stok’s sublime The Philosopher, the Dog and the Wedding.&#xA;The book is a beautiful and meticulously researched graphic novel that reimagines Hipparchia’s life, and explores what we might learn from it.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Swoop and Surge of Life: Lucretius on Ethics in Motion</title>
      <link>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/lucretius-ethics/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jun 2022 10:00:53 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/lucretius-ethics/</guid>
      <description>Love, Strife and The Mad Machinery of War In his great poem, On the Nature of the Universe (De Rerum Natura), Roman poet-philosopher Lucretius (born c. 100 BCE) asks what it means to live fully in a world where everything is always in motion. A follower of the Greek philosopher Epicurus, Lucretius proposed that the universe was both dynamic and unstable. But as well as setting out a vision of physics, or how the world is, Lucretius also set out a compelling vision of what it means to live in such a world.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>7 Ways of Reading Philosophy #5: Reading While Drunk</title>
      <link>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/7-ways-05-drunk/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Jun 2022 09:16:49 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/7-ways-05-drunk/</guid>
      <description>Philosophers Behaving Badly? The philosopher Simone de Beauvoir was a big fan of philosophising while drunk. Along with her sidekick Jean Paul Sartre, De Beauvoir partied hard, with the full commitment you might expect given her existentialist tendencies. In this, she was part of a long tradition of philosophers who drink. This tradition is so well established that the bar-room philosopher has become a stock figure in popular mythology: the drunken rambler who lists across the room and corners you for a conversation about how you can be certain that the tables and chairs in the bar really exist.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Lucretius on Chance, Necessity and Free Will</title>
      <link>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/lucretius-clinamen/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 May 2022 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/lucretius-clinamen/</guid>
      <description>The Philosopher and the Love Potion If you were to trust Saint Jerome – and you probably shouldn&amp;rsquo;t – the philosopher and poet Titus Lucretius Carus, better known simply as Lucretius, met an unfortunate end. The philosopher-poet was born some time after 100 BCE, a Roman citizen, and he became a follower of the atomism of Democritus and the materialist teachings of Epicurus, who emphasised the role of pleasure in human life.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Combat, Play and Aesthetic Experience: Three Metaphors of Philosophy</title>
      <link>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/combat-play-and-aesthetic-experience/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 May 2022 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/combat-play-and-aesthetic-experience/</guid>
      <description>Two Men, Fighting You don&amp;rsquo;t notice it at first.&#xA;The two men are fighting it out with big sticks. One has blood streaming down his face. He lifts his arm to bring his cudgel down hard on his opponent&amp;rsquo;s head. The other man lifts his arm to protect himself, while reaching back to swing his own club from the side.&#xA;We don&amp;rsquo;t know why they are fighting, or over what. Maybe they are battling for something important.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Advice for Rulers, Charioteers and Cyclists: the Huainanzi</title>
      <link>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/huainanzi/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 Apr 2022 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/huainanzi/</guid>
      <description>The Many Voices of the Huainanzi In the year 139 BCE, Liu An (劉安 179-122 BCE), the scholarly-minded King of Huainan, wanted to ingratiate himself to his cousin once removed, the Emperor Wu of Han. So he did what any self-respecting scholar king would do. Anxious to demonstrate his usefulness and his political nous, he convened a group of scholars to put together a text on the art of leadership to present to the young emperor.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Knowing, Doing, and Doubting: Nyāya Philosophy</title>
      <link>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/nyaya/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Apr 2022 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/nyaya/</guid>
      <description>Texts and Woven Threads The tradition of Nyāya philosophy in India goes back to a text called the Nyāya-sūtra. It is one of the most extensive treatments of the art of reasoning to be found in early Indian philosophy.&#xA;The Nyāya-sūtra is a fascinating text, one that explores the relationship between knowing, practical action, and doubt. The various strands in the sūtra (the word “sūtra&amp;quot; सूत्र means “thread”) were probably brought together into something resembling the current form around 150 in the Common Era.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Constellations of Thought: God, Death, and Other Non-Problems</title>
      <link>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/constellations-of-thought/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Apr 2022 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/constellations-of-thought/</guid>
      <description>Loneliness, Mortality and Terror Okay, folks! Strap in for an extended philosopher file, where we&amp;rsquo;re talking about fundamental problems in philosophy, why there may be no such things, what it might mean to approach philosophy more like an anthropologist, and how to redraw our maps of human life.&#xA;Several years ago, I attended an academic conference on philosophy. Some way through the conference, mid-afternoon, at the point when everybody was becoming a bit somnolent, I found myself in a half-empty university teaching room, my notebook in front of me.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dong Zhongshu&#39;s Tales of the Unexpected</title>
      <link>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/dong-zhongshu/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 31 Mar 2022 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/dong-zhongshu/</guid>
      <description>Chronicles and Caterpillars If there&amp;rsquo;s anything that we can predict with certainty about the course of history, it is that history is unpredictable. This is an insight that was central to the thought of the Chinese philosopher Dong Zhongshu (董仲舒).&#xA;Dong was born some time around 198 BCE in Guangchuan, now in present-day Hebei. What we know about his life comes from a couple of sources. First, a few scrappy references in the Shiji (史記) or Records of the Grand Historian, by the historian Sima Qian (司馬遷).</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Kaṇāda&#39;s Search for a Soul Without Qualities</title>
      <link>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/kanada/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Mar 2022 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/kanada/</guid>
      <description>The Soul and Other Long-standing Problems What is the soul? What is our innermost essence? What makes us, most deeply, who we are?&#xA;When faced by this question, the temptation is to go straight to our uniqueness. What makes me me is that I have unique, singular, specific qualities. This uniqueness and singularity is what is most deeply, and most fundamentally, who I am.&#xA;But for the Indian philosopher Kaṇāda, the opposite is true.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>7 Ways of Reading Philosophy : #4 Reading Out Loud</title>
      <link>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/7-ways-04-out-loud/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Mar 2022 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/7-ways-04-out-loud/</guid>
      <description>The Silent Reader There&amp;rsquo;s a story that Saint Augustine (354 – 430 CE) tells about his meeting with Ambrose, the bishop of Milan. When Augustine turned up in Milan, it was in search of a teacher of rhetoric. And Ambrose was considered one of the best.&#xA;At the time, Augustine&amp;rsquo;s philosophical and religious commitments were to the doctrines of Manichaeanism. He was unimpressed by Ambrose&amp;rsquo;s Catholic teachings, even while he was impressed by his new mentor&amp;rsquo;s kindness and rhetorical skill.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Learning to Play the Piano With Ptolemaïs of Cyrene</title>
      <link>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/ptolemais/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Mar 2022 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/ptolemais/</guid>
      <description>Learning to Play At the moment, I&amp;rsquo;m endeavouring to improve my rudimentary jazz piano playing. It&amp;rsquo;s a long process: I&amp;rsquo;ve played on and off for years, without really getting any better. So this year, now I&amp;rsquo;ve been reunited with my keyboard, I&amp;rsquo;ve been trying to put some more time in, hoping that I can make some small, incremental improvements. It&amp;rsquo;s fun, fascinating and sometimes frustrating.&#xA;There&amp;rsquo;s a lot to learn: all that theory, that experience of listening to music, that feeling of what the music is like in your bones.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Charisma of No-Charisma: Han Fei, Law, and the Art of Politics</title>
      <link>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/han-fei/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Feb 2022 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/han-fei/</guid>
      <description>Philosophy in times of strife The Chinese Legalist philosopher Han Fei (韓非) (281-233 BCE) was born a member of the royal household in the small state of Han. What we know about Han Fei comes from the unreliable Records of the Grand Historian by Sima Qian. The stories may not be entirely trustworthy, but we do know that the context of Han Fei&amp;rsquo;s life was one of the political strife that marked the centuries known in China as the Warring States period (dating from 476 to 221 BCE).</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Renegade Philosophers, and the Art of Changing Your Mind</title>
      <link>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/renegade-philosophers/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Feb 2022 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/renegade-philosophers/</guid>
      <description>Does philosophy change our minds? Philosophers talk a lot about the power of reasoned argument to change our minds. The whole discipline of philosophy, to an extent, depends on the idea that this is how argument works.&#xA;But there&amp;rsquo;s a problem with this idea. Because one thing that you notice if you hang around philosophers for a while is that in practice, they don&amp;rsquo;t change their minds very often. Surely, one might think, if reasoned debate were really this transformative, then their skill in the use of reason would lead to them changing their minds with a quicksilver frequency that would put the rest of us to shame.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Zou Yan, Yin and Yang, and the Nature of Change</title>
      <link>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/zou-yan/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Feb 2022 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/zou-yan/</guid>
      <description>The philosophical alchemist The philosopher Zou Yan (鄒衍) lived between 305 and 240CE. He is associated with the so-called Yin Yang School (yinyang jia 陰陽家), also sometimes referred to as the school of Chinese naturalism.&#xA;What biographical information we have about Zou Yan comes from Sima Qian&amp;rsquo;s Shiji or Records of the Grand Historian. The Shiji says that Zou Yan came from the state of Qi. His written output was considerable, and it encompassed everything from geography and natural history to history and philosophy.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sounds Plausible? The Philosophy of Carneades</title>
      <link>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/carneades/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Jan 2022 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/carneades/</guid>
      <description>Obsession and self-medication The philosopher Carneades was born in Cyrene, home of the Cyrenaic philosophers, sometime around 214 BCE. Like many philosophers of his day in the Greek-speaking world, he moved to Athens so he could further his studies.&#xA;Contemporary accounts of Carneades paint him as an obsessive, single-minded type. He was so engrossed by his studies that he didn&amp;rsquo;t cut his nails or his hair, and he had to be persuaded to eat, because otherwise he would simply forget.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Justifying Ritual with Jaimini</title>
      <link>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/jaimini/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Jan 2022 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/jaimini/</guid>
      <description>Killed by an elephant The philosopher Jaimini is an obscure figure. We know almost nothing about him, other than the story – which may or may not be true – that he was killed by a rampaging elephant. But beyond this, the records are silent.&#xA;Although he is known as the founder of the mīmāṃsā philosophical school, we don&amp;rsquo;t even know which century Jaimini lived in. The best guest for a date for the Mīmāṃsā-Sūtra, the foundational text of the mīmāṃsā philosophical tradition attributed to Jaimini, is sometime around 200 BCE, although some scholars date it to a couple of centuries earlier.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Desmond Tutu, Ubuntu and the Possibility of Hope</title>
      <link>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/ubuntu/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 Jan 2022 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/ubuntu/</guid>
      <description>Truth, Reconciliation, and Ubuntu The day after Christmas day last year marked the death of Desmond Mpilo Tutu (1931 - 2021), the Nobel Prizewinner, anti-apartheid activist and former archbishop of Cape Town.&#xA;Tutu&amp;rsquo;s life was extraordinary, as is his legacy. Born in 1931 to Tswana and Xhosa parents, he studied theology in London before returning to his native South Africa, where he became a powerful voice in the fight against apartheid.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Andy West on Philosophy, Prison, Freedom and Shame</title>
      <link>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/andy-west/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Dec 2021 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/andy-west/</guid>
      <description>Introduction Andy West is Philosopher in Residence at HMP Pentonville, and the author of the frankly brilliant The Life Inside: A Memoir of Prison, Family and Philosophy, which is due out from Picador in February 2022.&#xA;Q: One of the reasons I’m interested in doing these interviews is I want to get a sense of what it means to do philosophy. So my first question is this: how did you get into philosophy?</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Getting Smart About Pleasure: The Philosophy of Epicurus</title>
      <link>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/epicurus/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 Dec 2021 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/epicurus/</guid>
      <description>Taking pleasure seriously The Greek philosopher Epicurus is a philosopher most often associated with hedonism, the idea that the good life is a life where we should seek to maximise our pleasure. This might conjure up images of wild excess, or endless drug-fuelled orgies. And this, in fact, is how Epicurus&amp;rsquo;s opponents sometimes represented his philosophy and his community of followers. But Epicurus&amp;rsquo;s own approach to living pleasurably was more sedate than his critics imagined.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Tastiness of the Gift</title>
      <link>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/the-tastiness-of-the-gift/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Nov 2021 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/the-tastiness-of-the-gift/</guid>
      <description>The puzzle of gift-giving It&amp;rsquo;s the time of year when, for those of us who live in countries and communities where Christmas is celebrated, we face the prospect of an explosion of gift exchange. This gift-giving raises all kinds of practical issues (as we asked in the last philosopher file, what do you get a man like Uncle Pedro?). But it is also philosophically puzzling. Why do we do it? What&amp;rsquo;s going on in this frenzy of giving and receiving gifts?</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Philosophy of Giving</title>
      <link>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/philosophy-of-giving/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Nov 2021 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/philosophy-of-giving/</guid>
      <description>So, in those countries where Christmas is celebrated, it&amp;rsquo;s getting to that time of year when the eternal philosophical problem presents itself: *what should I get as a gift for Uncle Pedro?&#xA;Last year&amp;rsquo;s socks didn&amp;rsquo;t go down well: he didn&amp;rsquo;t wear them even once. Then there was the debacle with the chocolate (how had you never known that Uncle Pedro was allergic to cocoa beans)? As for the six-volume boxed set of Proust that you bought him, he hasn&amp;rsquo;t even cracked the spine on the first volume.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Chrysippus on How to Manage Our Emotions</title>
      <link>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/chrysippus/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Nov 2021 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/chrysippus/</guid>
      <description>The philosopher who couldn&amp;rsquo;t hold his drink Chrysippus was born sometime around 279 BCE in the town of Soli, now on the southern coast of Turkey. Diogenes Laërtius says that Chrysippus first trained as a long-distance runner, but eventually, he came to Athens and became fascinated by Stoicism. He became a follower of Cleanthes (c. 330 — c. 230 BC), himself a disciple of Zeno of Citium, and when Cleanthes died, Chrysippus took over as head of the Stoic school.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ritual Shapes the World</title>
      <link>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/ritual-and-creativity/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Oct 2021 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/ritual-and-creativity/</guid>
      <description>Ritual is a Creative Act This is the second in a two-part series on ritual. In the first piece, we looked at how ritual helps us get by, sometimes almost magically, in a complicated social world (you can read part one of this series here).&#xA;But ritual is more than just a way of getting by. It is also a way of giving shape to ourselves and our shared world. To engage in ritual is to engage in a creative act that can transform the world.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>It&#39;s a Kind of Magic: The Philosophy of Ritual</title>
      <link>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/philosophy-of-ritual/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Oct 2021 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/philosophy-of-ritual/</guid>
      <description>Looking at the overlooked Sometimes, the most philosophically interesting things in human life are those things that are so close to us, we overlook their importance. So in the next couple of pieces here in Looking for Wisdom, I&amp;rsquo;m going to explore one of these philosophically interesting, but often hidden, topics: and that topic is ritual.&#xA;When we hear the word “ritual”, what often comes to mind is something pretty elaborate, involving fancy outfits, the recitation of obscure texts, long robes, even longer faces, and altars fragrant with incense.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Pyrrho and the Trouble with Ethics</title>
      <link>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/pyrrho/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 07 Oct 2021 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/pyrrho/</guid>
      <description>Cultural connections The philosopher Pyrrho (c. 360 — c. 270 BCE) was born in Elis in Western Greece. Much of what we know about him is hearsay, deriving from the somewhat breathless accounts of his student and all-round biggest philosophical fan, Timon of Phlius. Timon&amp;rsquo;s stories, whether true or not, were later taken up by the biographer Diogenes Laërtius. Diogenes supplemented Timon&amp;rsquo;s admiring accounts with some intriguing tales about Pyrrho&amp;rsquo;s eccentricities taken from the writer Antigonus of Carystus.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hipparchia: Philosophy as Comedy</title>
      <link>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/hipparchia/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Sep 2021 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/hipparchia/</guid>
      <description>Living the Cynic Life Somewhere between a philosopher, a comedian, and an activist, Hipparchia of Maroneia was one of the most significant early philosophers in the Cynic school founded by Diogenes. She was born some time around 350 BCE in the Thracian village of Maroneia, but when she was still young, she moved with her family to Athens. Her background was privileged and wealthy. However, along with her brother Metrocles, once in Athens, she became involved with the Cynic philosophers.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Zeno of Citium and the Challenge of Living Naturally</title>
      <link>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/zeno-of-citium/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Sep 2021 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/zeno-of-citium/</guid>
      <description>The first Stoic Zeno of Citium—not to be confused with Zeno of Elea—was the founder of the Stoic school of philosophy. In recent years, Stoicism has seen a huge resurgence, both as an area of academic interest, and also as a popular philosophy offering guidance in our everyday lives. But how did it all begin?&#xA;Life Zeno (334-262 BCE) came from the city of Citium in Cyprus, but like many philosophers of his day, he eventually ended up in Athens, the intellectual hub of the ancient Greek world.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Not the Mystical East: India&#39;s Long Tradition of Materialism</title>
      <link>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/indian-materialism/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Sep 2021 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/indian-materialism/</guid>
      <description>A This-Worldly Philosophy In popular culture, there can be a tendency to see Indian philosophical traditions as somehow inherently spiritual, and to contrast this supposedly mystical East with a rational West. But this division of the world into a rational West and a mystical East maps poorly onto the facts. Much philosophy in the West, from Plato and Socrates onwards, is tangled up with various forms of mysticism, and with a preoccupation with the divine.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sophie Grace Chappell on Plato and the Moral Imagination</title>
      <link>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/sophie-grace-chappell/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Aug 2021 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/sophie-grace-chappell/</guid>
      <description>On Philosophy, Mountains and Finding Your Deepest Impulse Sophie Grace Chappell is a philosopher, a poet, a mountaineer and a trans woman. She was born in Lancashire in 1964, and educated at Bolton School and Magdalen College, Oxford. She has taught at Oxford, UEA, Manchester, and Dundee. Since 1998, she has lived in Dundee with her family.&#xA;Her last book is Knowing What To Do (OUP 2014), and her next book is Epiphanies (OUP 2022).</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Aristotle on Flourishing</title>
      <link>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/aristotle-on-flourishing/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Aug 2021 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/aristotle-on-flourishing/</guid>
      <description>What&amp;rsquo;s the Point? What&amp;rsquo;s the point? Some time or other, we&amp;rsquo;ve all probably asked ourselves this question. What&amp;rsquo;s the point of doing what we are doing? What&amp;rsquo;s the point of our lives? What&amp;rsquo;s the point of human life in general?&#xA;When we ask ourselves these questions, we are not just idly speculating about life. Instead, these are questions that we feel deeply and intensely. They have an existential weight behind them.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Aristotle on Ways of Knowing</title>
      <link>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/aristotle/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Aug 2021 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/aristotle/</guid>
      <description>Life Aristotle is one of the most influential of all philosophers in the Greek tradition. He was Plato&amp;rsquo;s most famous student, but he ended up rejecting many of Plato&amp;rsquo;s central ideas, in particular his theory of forms. And he was a formative influence not only on the philosophical traditions of Europe but also on those of the Islamic world.&#xA;However, if the ancient biographer Diogenes Laërtius is to be believed (which, alas, he isn&amp;rsquo;t always), Aristotle was quite a curious individual.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hui Shi and the Power of Analogy</title>
      <link>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/hui-shi/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Aug 2021 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/hui-shi/</guid>
      <description>Life Hui Shi (c. 370 — c. 310 BCE) was a Chinese philosopher known for his fascination with logical puzzles. He is considered as a representative of the School of Names, or in Chinese ming jia (see the philosopher file on Deng Xi). Hui Shi is famous, in particular, for his puzzling paradoxes that seem to share some resemblances with those of Zeno of Elea.&#xA;As with so many figures in early Chinese thought, the historical Hui Shi is frustratingly elusive.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Plato&#39;s Theory of Forms</title>
      <link>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/plato-part-two/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 Jul 2021 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/plato-part-two/</guid>
      <description>Plato&amp;rsquo;s so-called &amp;rsquo;theory of forms&amp;rsquo; is one of the most enduringly strange parts of his philosophy. It is also one of the main centres of gravity around which Plato&amp;rsquo;s work turns. So in the second part of our two-part philosopher file on Plato, we&amp;rsquo;re going to look at this theory in more depth.&#xA;If you want more background information on Plato, you can go to part one and read the piece there.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Xunzi on Crafting Ourselves</title>
      <link>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/xunzi/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 Jul 2021 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/xunzi/</guid>
      <description>Life Like Confucius and Mencius before him, it is said that the Confucian philosopher Xun Kuang, or Xunzi (c. 310 – 235 BCE), was an itinerant advisor to kings and rulers.&#xA;Not much is known about his early life. But there are indications that in his later years as a political advisor, he had more success than both Mencius and Confucius. He was appointed to several high positions, before eventually retiring from public life and living out the remainder of his years far from the intrigues of politics.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Aztec Philosophy and the Slipperiness of the World</title>
      <link>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/aztec-philosophy/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 08 Jul 2021 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/aztec-philosophy/</guid>
      <description>The Aztecs and Philosophy Who were the Aztecs? The people now usually called the Aztecs were a Nahuatl-speaking people from Central Mexico. From the thirteenth century, their ancestors migrated from what is now Northern Mexico and the Southern United States to Mexico&amp;rsquo;s high central plateau. In the long political struggle for dominance that followed, the Aztecs eventually settled on a marshy, unprepossessing island in the middle of Lake Texcoco, where they began to build up a regional power base that became the foundation of one of the world&amp;rsquo;s greatest empires.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Free and Easy Rambling With Zhuangzi</title>
      <link>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/zhuangzi/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Jul 2021 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/zhuangzi/</guid>
      <description>Zhuangzi: The Philosopher and the Text Zhuangzi (sometimes written Chuang Tzu), or Master Zhuang, is the name given to the philosopher Zhuang Zhou, who lived in China sometime between 369 and 286 BCE. The book that takes the philosopher&amp;rsquo;s name, the Zhuangzi, is almost certainly the work of several hands. And although the book doesn&amp;rsquo;t present a coherent viewpoint, it does have an overarching mood: a free-wheeling, almost anarchistic blend of humour and insight, one that may reflect the character of the historical Zhuang Zhou.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Arete of Cyrene and the Smooth Motion of the Flesh</title>
      <link>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/arete/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Jun 2021 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/arete/</guid>
      <description>Life Arete of Cyrene was born into a philosophically-inclined family. Her father, Aristippus of Cyrene (c. 430 – 356 BCE), founded a distinctive philosophical school, known as the Cyrenaics, named after his home town, near Shahhat in present-day Libya.&#xA;We know slightly more about Aristippus than we do about his daughter Arete. He travelled to Athens when he was still a young man, and he became a part of the circle surrounding Socrates, although they had very different philosophical approaches.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Future of Work (Work #7)</title>
      <link>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/work07-the-future/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Jun 2021 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/work07-the-future/</guid>
      <description>Welcome to the final piece in our season three series on the philosophy of work. Over the last couple of months, we&amp;rsquo;ve been putting work under the philosophical microscope, and exploring why it plays such an important part in our lives.&#xA;In this final article, we&amp;rsquo;re going to go back over the territory we have covered, to see if we can now throw more light on the complex roles played by work in human life.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mencius and the Sprouts of Virtue</title>
      <link>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/mencius/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Jun 2021 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/mencius/</guid>
      <description>Life In China, Mencius is sometimes referred to as the Second Sage, meaning that in the Confucian tradition, he is second only to Confucius in importance. China&amp;rsquo;s Second Sage was born in the 4th century BCE in the state of Zou, in what is now present-day Shandong province. His estimated dates are either 372 – 289 BCE or 385 – c. 303 BCE.&#xA;Mencius&amp;rsquo;s given name was Meng Ke. The name “Mengzi”, means “master Meng”, the suffix zi being an honorific.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Opposite of Work Part 2: Philosophy and Play (Work #6)</title>
      <link>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/work06-philosophy-and-play/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 07 Jun 2021 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/work06-philosophy-and-play/</guid>
      <description>In the last article in this series, we started exploring the opposite of work. If we want to understand the role that work has in human life, it is useful to think about all the things that we don&amp;rsquo;t consider to be work.&#xA;Often we understand what things are in terms of what they are not. And this is certainly the case with work. So, we define work in opposition to other things that we see as non-work—for example idleness, or play.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Plato&#39;s Cave, and Escaping the Prison of Ignorance</title>
      <link>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/plato-part-one/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 03 Jun 2021 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/plato-part-one/</guid>
      <description>Life The great ventriloquist Plato was born in Athens some time between 428 and 423 BCE to a high-ranking Athenian family. Plato&amp;rsquo;s family took particular pride in being related to the great statesman Solon who lived two centuries before, and who put in place the laws that underpinned Athenian democracy.&#xA;Like many other philosophers in Ancient Greece, Plato wrote his philosophical works in a literary form. But where Parmenides and Xenophanes wrote in verse, Plato&amp;rsquo;s preferred form was dialogue.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Opposite of Work? All About Idleness (Work #5)</title>
      <link>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/work05-all-about-idleness/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 31 May 2021 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/work05-all-about-idleness/</guid>
      <description>Over the last four articles in this series, we have been exploring divergent ideas of work. What is work? What role does it play in human life? How can we think better about work? Is work our salvation or our ruin? Is it the path that leads to virtue, or does it lead to our own destruction?&#xA;But when you start to think about work, you are also—by implication at least—thinking about non-work.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spiritual Damage: How Work is Bad for Us (Work #4)</title>
      <link>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/work04-spiritual-damage/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 May 2021 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/work04-spiritual-damage/</guid>
      <description>In last week&amp;rsquo;s piece, we explored how work might of benefit to us—how it might even be our salvation. For some thinkers, work is inherently ennobling and self-improving. It is, as Carlyle put it, a “purifying fire, wherein all poison is burnt up.”&#xA;Even if we don&amp;rsquo;t go as far as Carlyle, we have already seen that work can be beneficial in that it provides us with a range of both internal and external goods.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Zeno of Elea on Why Change is an Illusion</title>
      <link>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/zeno-of-elea/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 May 2021 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/zeno-of-elea/</guid>
      <description>Life Zeno of Elea is another of those shadowy ancient philosophers about whom we know very little. According to some accounts, he was the student of both Parmenides and Xenophanes.&#xA;Zeno appears in Plato&amp;rsquo;s Parmenides, where he is visiting Athens together with his teacher. There, the two philosophers meet the young Socrates, upon whom Zeno makes a substantial impression. If Plato&amp;rsquo;s story is true, this would mean that Zeno was born some time around 490 BCE.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>7 Ways of Reading Philosophy: #3 Reading self-interestedly</title>
      <link>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/7-ways-03-self-interest/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 May 2021 10:48:44 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/7-ways-03-self-interest/</guid>
      <description>In the last article in this series on different approaches to reading philosophy, I talked about the rights of the reader to plot a course through whatever they are reading in whatever way they wish—doubling-back, skipping, haphazard and unsystematic, leaving books unfinished.&#xA;A reader who does this might seem, to their more sober peers, to be wilfully irresponsible, or failing in their duties as a reader. But in this article, I want to push the virtues of non-dutiful reading a little further, and I want to argue that one fruitful way of reading philosophy (and, for that matter, anything else) is to read out of self-interest.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Goodness of Work: Virtue, work, and salvation (Work #3)</title>
      <link>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/work03-virtue-salvation/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 May 2021 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/work03-virtue-salvation/</guid>
      <description>In this article, we&amp;rsquo;re going to explore the idea that there is something inherently good about work, that work may in some sense be our salvation.&#xA;Probably all of us grumble about our work from time to time. But for all our grumbling, we often see work in itself as a good thing. We praise people for working hard, and we criticise them for slacking off. We tell each other how hard we are working, and when we do, we feel the warm glow of virtue.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Maya Philosophy, and How to Give Shape to Time</title>
      <link>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/maya-philosophy/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 May 2021 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/maya-philosophy/</guid>
      <description>Understanding the world The story of philosophy is the story of human attempts to understand the world of which we are a part, and to understand ourselves. But traditions of academic philosophy have tended to give greater weight to only a small handful of traditions — for example, Greek and European philosophy, Indian philosophy or Chinese philosophy.&#xA;But if philosophy is really about human attempts to understand the world, and to understand what it means to be human, then if we limit ourselves to a few traditions, we risk missing out on rich resources.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Life of Activity: Work, Labour and Action (Work #2)</title>
      <link>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/work02-the-life-of-activity/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 May 2021 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/work02-the-life-of-activity/</guid>
      <description>What is work? And how can we think better about work? Like many other things, we more or less know what work is when we don&amp;rsquo;t think about it too hard. But when we try to think a bit more deeply, or a bit more systematically, it becomes harder to figure out. So in this piece, we&amp;rsquo;ll be looking at the philosopher Hannah Arendt, whose exploration of the vita activa, or “the active life”, is a useful way to start getting a handle on the role that work plays in human life.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mozi and the Challenge of Universal Love</title>
      <link>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/mozi/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 May 2021 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/mozi/</guid>
      <description>Life The philosopher Mo Di, more commonly known as Mozi (or “Master Mo”) lived sometime between the fifth and fourth centuries BCE. Although we don&amp;rsquo;t have a great deal of information about Mozi as an individual, the evidence suggests he was born, as was Confucius, in the state of Lu. Many later writers have suggested that he came from the artisan class, and thus was something of an outsider to the high society of Warring States China.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Working it Out: The Philosophy of Work (Work #1)</title>
      <link>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/work01-working-it-out/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 May 2021 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/work01-working-it-out/</guid>
      <description>Welcome Welcome to the latest Looking for Wisdom philosophy course, where we&amp;rsquo;ll be exploring the philosophy of work.&#xA;We spend much of our lives working, and much of the time when we are not working, we spend talking about work, recovering from work, fretting about work, or wondering if we should work more or work less. But what is work? Why does it loom so large in our lives? And how can philosophy help throw more light on what work is, and why it matters?</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Democritus and Reasons to be Cheerful</title>
      <link>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/democritus/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 Apr 2021 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/democritus/</guid>
      <description>Life Democritus was born in the city of Abdera in Thrace sometime around 460 BCE. Later accounts say he studied with the philosopher Leucippus. Leucippus is said to have authored two books: On Mind and The Great World System, neither of which has survived. Democritus was much more prolific and is said to have authored up to seventy works.&#xA;Between them, Leucippus and Democritus introduced a new idea into the Greek philosophical world: the idea that the things of the universe were constructed out of innumerable, infinitesimally small building blocks that they called atoms.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Yang Zhu on How to Keep Our Nature Intact</title>
      <link>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/yang-zhu/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 Apr 2021 11:15:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/yang-zhu/</guid>
      <description>Life Yang Zhu, also known as Yangzi or “Master Yang”, was a Chinese philosopher who lived sometime around the fourth or fifth century BCE, during the Warring States Period in China. We know very little about Yang Zhu himself, and what we know of his philosophy is based on the accounts of other, later writers.&#xA;Yang Zhu has always been a controversial philosopher, in part because of his robust emphasis on the importance of care for oneself.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>&#34;Love and Understanding&#34;: The tangle of love and wisdom (Love #7)</title>
      <link>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/love07-love-and-understanding/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Apr 2021 13:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/love07-love-and-understanding/</guid>
      <description>The Love of Wisdom, and the Wisdom of Love Welcome to the final piece in our series on love. In this article, we&amp;rsquo;re going to be looking at the idea of philosophy as the love of wisdom. And we&amp;rsquo;re going to ask about whether there is a deeper connection between wisdom and love.&#xA;The first person to talk about philosophy as the love of wisdom was the Greek philosopher Pythagoras. The idea that philosophy is the love of wisdom—rather than, for example, the practice of wisdom—puts a bit of a distance between us and the wisdom that we aspire to.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Gautama Buddha and the Turn Toward Experience</title>
      <link>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/gautama-buddha/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 08 Apr 2021 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/gautama-buddha/</guid>
      <description>Life All contemporary traditions of Buddhism trace their origins to a wandering sage-philosopher from India, sometimes called Siddhārtha Gautama, or simply known as “the Buddha.” The Buddha&amp;rsquo;s dates are not well-established: estimates range from between the sixth century BCE to the latter half of the 5th century BCE or even the early part of the 4th century BCE. And despite the vastness of the Buddhist textual tradition, the details of the Buddha&amp;rsquo;s life are still controversial.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>“Will You Still Love Me Tomorrow?” Love, trust and the future (Love #6)</title>
      <link>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/love06-will-you-still-love-me/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 05 Apr 2021 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/love06-will-you-still-love-me/</guid>
      <description>Introduction Imagine you&amp;rsquo;ve been dating somebody for a while. Things are going well. You like each other, and the dates are all enjoyable and fun. You are pretty happy with how things are progressing. But one day, the other person turns to you—an intense look on their face—and says in a tremulous voice, “I love you.”&#xA;You are stunned. Astonished. This puts things on a different footing. Everything has moved up a notch, and you are not sure how to respond.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Living the Life of a Dog with Diogenes the Cynic</title>
      <link>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/diogenes/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Apr 2021 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/diogenes/</guid>
      <description>Life Diogenes — also known as the Dog — was a native of the state of Sinope on the Black Sea coast. He was born around 410 BCE, by which time Sinope was a busy commercial hub, standing at the end of a trade route that stretched all the way to Mesopotamia.&#xA;According to early accounts of Diogenes&amp;rsquo;s life, his father Hicesias was in charge of managing the Sinope mint. But there was a scandal about counterfeit, defaced or adulterated coinage, which led to Diogenes fleeing into exile in Athens.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Love Lifts Us Up Where We Belong? Love, transcendence and madness (Love #5)</title>
      <link>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/love05-love-lifts-us-up/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Mar 2021 11:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/love05-love-lifts-us-up/</guid>
      <description>Love, we are told, lifts us up where we belong: “Where the eagles cry / On a mountain high… / Far from the world we know / Where the clear winds blow.”&#xA;When we are in love, the world takes on a different, more giddying perspective. But shifts in perspective are tricky things. When we are loved-up and out of our right minds, are we at last seeing the world clearly?</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>7 Ways of Reading Philosophy: #2 Reading haphazardly</title>
      <link>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/7-ways-02-haphazardly/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 Mar 2021 07:34:58 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/7-ways-02-haphazardly/</guid>
      <description>Philosophers and storytellers The moment you pick up a philosophy book, if you are anything like me, you will almost immediately feel heavy with a cluster of obligations. The obligation to understand. The obligation to take this great work seriously. And the obligation to read systematically, one page at a time.&#xA;But as I suggested in the previous article in this series on reading philosophy at a gallop, this approach can slow you down—to the extent that you end up grinding to a halt.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>You Sexy Thing: Getting philosophical about sex (Love #4)</title>
      <link>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/love04-you-sexy-thing/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Mar 2021 11:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/love04-you-sexy-thing/</guid>
      <description>A complicated business&amp;hellip; Of all areas of human life, sex is one of the most complicated. It is the place where biology, culture, ideas of the good life and weighty moral claims collide. Questions about sex are one of the great human preoccupations. Questions like: How much sex should we have? Should we have as much as possible? Or—like the Buddhist monks, wary of desire—should we choose to abstain? Whom should we have sex with?</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>7 Ways of Reading Philosophy: #1 Reading Like Napoleon</title>
      <link>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/7-ways-01-napoleon/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Mar 2021 11:30:32 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/7-ways-01-napoleon/</guid>
      <description>When reading philosophy, the advice is often to read slowly and carefully, tortoise-style, making sure you understand every point before going on to the next. But in this article — the second in my ongoing series on how to read philosophy — I want to persuade you that this can sometimes be the very worst approach. And to do so, I&amp;rsquo;m going to take my lead from the German philosopher Franz Rosenzweig (1886-1929).</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Finding Our Way With Laozi</title>
      <link>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/laozi/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Mar 2021 11:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/laozi/</guid>
      <description>Introduction The Daodejing or Classic of Ways and Powers is one of the most translated of all Chinese texts. It is traditionally attributed to the Daoist sage Laozi (also written Lao Tzu),&#xA;At just over 5000 characters long, the Daodejing is a masterpiece of compression. But due to its brevity and its elliptical style, it has been read in a multitude of different ways: as everything from a mystical treatise to a hard-headed work about statecraft.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Something So Right: Love and Justice (Love #3)</title>
      <link>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/love03-something-so-right/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Mar 2021 17:32:50 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/love03-something-so-right/</guid>
      <description>Taking your father to court The philosopher Socrates is outside the court in Athens. He has been accused of impiety and corrupting the minds of the youth of the city—a charge for which he will soon be executed. As he is idling in the street outside the courthouse, he comes across an earnest young man called Euthyphro. The young man is bringing a charge of murder against his father, something that is all but unthinkable in Athenian society.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>7 Ways of Reading Philosophy: An Introduction</title>
      <link>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/7-ways-introduction/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Mar 2021 11:40:51 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/7-ways-introduction/</guid>
      <description>Philosophy can often appear to be a daunting subject. All those great minds! All those long words! All those endless sentences that go on for half a page! The popular image of philosophy—an image that some philosophers are reluctant to dispel—is that it is an unusually difficult pursuit. And so perhaps it is not surprising that many readers sit down to read philosophy full of good intentions, only to find themselves grinding to a halt in a strange cocktail of frustration, inadequacy, and despair.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Alcmaeon of Croton, the First Philosopher of Medicine</title>
      <link>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/alcmaeon/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Mar 2021 11:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/alcmaeon/</guid>
      <description>Life According to Herodotus&amp;rsquo;s Histories, as far back as the sixth century BCE, the city of Croton in the south of Italy was famous as a centre for medicine. And so perhaps it is no surprise this was the home of one of the ancient world&amp;rsquo;s most famous philosophers of medicine, Alcmaeon.&#xA;We don&amp;rsquo;t know much about Alcmaeon&amp;rsquo;s life. He was probably born some time in the late sixth century BCE, which would make him a contemporary of the philosopher Parmenides.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>We All Stand Together: Love, connection and community (Love #2)</title>
      <link>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/love02-we-all-stand-together/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Mar 2021 11:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/love02-we-all-stand-together/</guid>
      <description>Social primates Whatever else it might be about, love is about connection. It is about how we relate to each other. It is about how we feel about others, how we think about them, how we connect with them, what we do with them. Love is not so much personal as interpersonal.&#xA;So one way to make inroads into thinking about love is by thinking about what it means to be live alongside others.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Alexus McLeod on Maya Philosophy</title>
      <link>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/alexus-mcleod-maya-philosophy/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Mar 2021 11:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/alexus-mcleod-maya-philosophy/</guid>
      <description>Introduction Alexus McLeod is originally from Washington, DC, and now living in West Hartford, Connecticut. He teaches at the University of Connecticut and writes on a host of topics: Chinese and Mesoamerican Philosophy, mysticism, political history, the history of science (particularly astronomy and medicine), and several other things besides. For much of the past year, like many of us, he has been living the hermit life. Camped out in his home office, he has continued his work exploring the riches of the world&amp;rsquo;s philosophical traditions.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Let&#39;s Do It: The Philosophy of Love (Love #1)</title>
      <link>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/love01-lets-do-it/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Mar 2021 11:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/love01-lets-do-it/</guid>
      <description>Welcome to our Season Two Looking for Wisdom Course Birds do it. Bees do it. And according to Cole Porter, even educated fleas do it (although I&amp;rsquo;m not quite so sure). But what is this thing called love? What does it mean to fall in love? And why does love loom so large in our individual and collective lives?&#xA;Welcome to season two in our Looking for Wisdom course series, where we&amp;rsquo;re going to be exploring the philosophy of love.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sunzi&#39;s Way of Deceit</title>
      <link>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/sunzi/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Feb 2021 11:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/sunzi/</guid>
      <description>Life Sunzi’s “The Art of War” is an ancient Chinese text that has become famous worldwide for its insights into strategy. But scratch the surface, and you find a text that is as troubling as it is fascinating.&#xA;If you are a business leader wanting to inject some gravitas and swagger into your PowerPoint presentation, then Sunzi’s The Art of War is the way to go. This ancient Chinese classic is often cited in the business world, at boardrooms and at training events.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Weaving the Net of Argument</title>
      <link>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/weaving-the-net/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Feb 2021 16:27:15 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/weaving-the-net/</guid>
      <description>Three radical women philosophers from the ancient world Although it is sometimes said that the history of philosophy is the history of human attempts to understand ourselves and the world, if you pick up any introductory philosophy textbook, it doesn&amp;rsquo;t take long to realise this isn&amp;rsquo;t quite true. Philosophy may claim to talk about human universals, but it&amp;rsquo;s hard to sustain this claim when most of the named figures in the historical traditions of the world are men: the history of philosophy is also the history of the exclusion of women&amp;rsquo;s voices from these conversations about what it means to be human.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Giving up on Philosophy? The Science of Wisdom (Wisdom #7)</title>
      <link>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/wisdom07-the-science-of-wisdom/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Feb 2021 11:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/wisdom07-the-science-of-wisdom/</guid>
      <description>Welcome to the final piece in this short series on wisdom. Over this series, we&amp;rsquo;ve explored a rich range of traditions to try and get a handle on what wisdom is (if it is anything at all), how it matters (if it matters), and how to cultivate it (if it is the kind of thing you can cultivate).&#xA;We&amp;rsquo;ve covered a lot of ground over the past few articles. So in this piece, we&amp;rsquo;re going to take a quick tour of the territory we have explored.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Empedocles on Love and Strife</title>
      <link>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/empedocles/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Feb 2021 11:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/empedocles/</guid>
      <description>Life Empedocles was a philosopher from the city of Akragas in Sicily. His traditional dates are around c. 494 BCE to c. 434 BCE, although these are uncertain. He came from a family of aristocrats, and his grandfather, also called Empedocles, was allegedly a skilled horseman who won the crown for his riding skills at the Olympic Games.&#xA;The dandyish shaman Some have argued that Empedocles studied with philosophers such as Xenophanes and Anaximander, although this is largely speculation.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Opposite of Wisdom: A Fool&#39;s Philosophy  (Wisdom #6)</title>
      <link>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/wisdom06-a-fools-philosophy/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Feb 2021 11:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/wisdom06-a-fools-philosophy/</guid>
      <description>If philosophy has always been preoccupied with wisdom, its relationship with the opposite of wisdom—foolishness—has always been a vexed one. One reason for this is that throughout the history of philosophy, the relationship between wisdom and foolishness has not been one of simple opposition. Instead, it seems that for some philosophers, at least, there is a kind of wisdom in foolishness.&#xA;We already know that Socrates was a self-confessed know-nothing. And also we know that for the Zhuangzi there is something wise in giving up in the pursuit of wisdom.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Deng Xi, the Philosopher Who Argued From Both Sides</title>
      <link>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/deng-xi/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Feb 2021 11:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/deng-xi/</guid>
      <description>Life Deng Xi (c. 545 - 501 BCE) was a lawyer from the state of Zheng, where he also served as an official. He is said to have written two works, but neither of them survive.&#xA;Deng Xi is chiefly famous for his unsettling approach to argument. He was famous for being able to &amp;rsquo;turn wrong into right and right into wrong,&amp;rsquo; and according to The Annals of Lü Buwei, he didn&amp;rsquo;t recognise any fixed standard for evaluating arguments.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Nurturing the Sprouts of Wisdom (Wisdom #5)</title>
      <link>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/wisdom05-nurturing-the-sprouts/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Feb 2021 11:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/wisdom05-nurturing-the-sprouts/</guid>
      <description>Wisdom, virtue and the art of cultivation If wisdom is something desirable, something to which we can aspire, then how do we go about becoming wiser? We saw in the second piece on Aristotle that wisdom involves both thinking (theoria) and doing (praxis). A wise person is somebody who thinks about things clearly and who also acts well. They have both intellectual and practical virtues. And ideally, these virtues support each other.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>That Gut Feeling: Wisdom and the body (Wisdom #4)</title>
      <link>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/wisdom04-that-gut-feeling/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 25 Jan 2021 11:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/wisdom04-that-gut-feeling/</guid>
      <description>Going with the gut How do we know what is the wise thing to do? What makes for a wise action? In the heat of the moment, how do we decide? If you talk to some philosophers, they might tell you that we simply have to reason things out. But experience suggests that things don&amp;rsquo;t work like this. More often than not, we don&amp;rsquo;t have time to sit down and theorise our way to an answer.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Anaxagoras on the Gunkiness of Reality</title>
      <link>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/anaxagoras/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Jan 2021 11:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/anaxagoras/</guid>
      <description>Anaxagoras: Life Anaxagoras was born into a wealthy family around the year 500 BCE in the city of Clazomenae, close to present-day Izmir on the coast of Turkey. When he was around twenty years old, he left Clazomenae for Athens. Accounts of why he moved to Athens differ: but some commentators claim that he left home because he was afraid that wealth and political power would get in the way of his pursuit of knowledge.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Limits of Wisdom (Wisdom #3)</title>
      <link>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/wisdom03-the-limits-of-wisdom/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 Jan 2021 11:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/wisdom03-the-limits-of-wisdom/</guid>
      <description>Socrates and Zhuang Zhou on not knowing Welcome back. In the previous piece, we saw how Aristotle carves up human activity to distinguish between production, chosen action and contemplation. And we looked at the distinction between theoretical wisdom and what Aristotle calls phronesis or practical wisdom. According to Aristotle, we can develop our faculties to become wiser, both in terms of how we think about the world and in terms of how we act.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Anna Ezekiel on Günderrode, Identity and Doing Philosophy Differently</title>
      <link>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/anna-ezekiel-karoline-von-gunderrode/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Jan 2021 11:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/anna-ezekiel-karoline-von-gunderrode/</guid>
      <description>Introduction Welcome to the first ever Philosopher File interview! In this interview, I&amp;rsquo;m talking to Anna Ezekiel, a philosopher originally from Scotland and now based in Hong Kong. Since 2014, Anna has worked as an independent scholar, living with ME / Chronic Fatigue Syndrome. She has a particular interest in German women philosophers.&#xA;Anna&amp;rsquo;s hugely readable and enjoyable translation of Karoline von Günderrode&amp;rsquo;s Poetic Fragments was published by SUNY Press 2016, and she is currently working on a further book of translations by Günderrode called Philosophical Fragments.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Navigating Wisdom with Aristotle (Wisdom #2)</title>
      <link>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/wisdom02-navigating-wisdom/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 Jan 2021 11:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/wisdom02-navigating-wisdom/</guid>
      <description>Wisdom, thinking and doing Welcome to the second piece in this series on wisdom: what it is and why it matters. In this piece, we&amp;rsquo;re going to be plunging into the work of Aristotle, one of Ancient Greece&amp;rsquo;s most profound thinkers, to ask about the relationship between wisdom, thinking and doing.&#xA;Wisdom, as we saw in the last essay, is more complex than it first seems. When we say someone is wise, we are not saying they possess just a single quality.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Xenophanes on Gods and Horses</title>
      <link>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/xenophanes/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 07 Jan 2021 11:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/xenophanes/</guid>
      <description>Life Xenophanes (c. 570 BCE — c. 478 BCE) came from the Ionian city of Colophon. He was a poet, a philosopher and an itinerant wanderer, who roamed around Ancient Greece from city to city, and sung his verses like a philosophical busker.&#xA;We don&amp;rsquo;t know a lot for certain about Xenophanes&amp;rsquo;s long life. He is said to have been teacher to the philosopher Parmenides. He may have been sold into slavery, and later released.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>What is Wisdom? (Wisdom #1)</title>
      <link>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/wisdom01-what-is-wisdom/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Jan 2021 11:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/wisdom01-what-is-wisdom/</guid>
      <description>Welcome This is the first in a seven-part series on wisdom. Over this series of articles, we&amp;rsquo;re going to be asking what wisdom is (if it is anything at all), how it matters (if it matters), and how to cultivate it (if it is the kind of thing you can cultivate).&#xA;In an everyday sense, we seem to have a pretty good grasp of what we mean when we talk about wisdom.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Jing Jiang on Politics, Gender and Weaving</title>
      <link>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/jing-jiang/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Dec 2020 11:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/jing-jiang/</guid>
      <description>Life Far-ranging wisdom Jing Jiang was a Chinese philosopher who was born in the state of Lu around 540 BCE. She appears in the Discourses of the States, or Guoyu, a text that dates to between the fifth and fourth centuries BCE. She is also featured in the later Biographies of Exemplary Women or Lienü Zhuang, an anthology compiled in by the scholar Liu Xiang who lived between 77 BCE and 6 BCE.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Parmenides on Truth and Opinion</title>
      <link>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/parmenides/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Dec 2020 11:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/parmenides/</guid>
      <description>Life Parmenides was a philosopher from the city of Elea, a Greek colony on the Italian peninsula. He was born some time around 515 BCE into a wealthy family. It was said that he had a sharp legal mind, and he was responsible for drawing up the laws of the city. He may also have been a student of the philosopher Xenophanes of Colophon, although this is disputed; and there is evidence he was influenced by the Pythagorean philosophers.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Yājñavalkya and the Immortal Self</title>
      <link>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/yajnavalkya/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Dec 2020 11:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/yajnavalkya/</guid>
      <description>Life Telling tales about the sages There is considerable debate about whether Yājñavalkya is a historical figure or a literary creation (see the Philosopher File on Diotima). If there was a historical figure called Yājñavalkya, his dates would be some time around the 7th century BCE. However, as the scholar Steven Lindquist writes, &amp;lsquo;The textual evidence as we have it does not appear to lend itself, as far as I can determine, to drawing an objective line regarding the historicity of Yājñavalkya.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Anaximander and the Boundlessly Creative Universe</title>
      <link>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/anaximander/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 03 Dec 2020 11:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/anaximander/</guid>
      <description>Life The first scientist? The philosopher Anaximander was born in the trading port of Miletus in 610 BCE, and is said to have become a student of the philosopher Thales. He was fascinated by processes of generation and destruction in the natural world. It is for this reason that the physicist Carlo Rovelli has called Anaximander &amp;rsquo;the first scientist&#39;:&#xA;He paved the way for physics, geography, meteorology, and biology. Even more important than these contributions, he set in motion the process of rethinking our worldview—a search for knowledge based on the rejection of any obvious-seeming “certainty,” which is one of the main roots of scientific thinking.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Plato: Organist to the Beasts</title>
      <link>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/plato-organist-to-the-beasts/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Dec 2020 08:30:08 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/plato-organist-to-the-beasts/</guid>
      <description>It&amp;rsquo;s a curious image. The philosopher Plato, dressed in a turban and a sash, sits before a pipe organ and plays sweet tunes. Meanwhile, around him lies a catatonic tribe of lions, tigers, antelopes, leopards, deer, rhinos, cranes, phoenixes and other beasts. What&amp;rsquo;s going on here? Are these animals sleeping? Are they dead? What is Plato up to?&#xA;It&amp;rsquo;s a strange and fascinating scene, so yesterday — not having much else to do under lockdown — I set about finding out more.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Gārgī Vācaknavī, the Eloquent Philosopher</title>
      <link>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/gargi/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Nov 2020 11:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/gargi/</guid>
      <description>Life Gārgī Vācaknavī appears in the Bṛhadāraṅyaka Upaniṣad, a philosophical compilation that dates to around the seventh or the sixth century BCE, although it contains strains of material that may be much older. She is one of the earliest named women philosophers in the Indian tradition, and may have lived some time around 700 BCE. Her name Gārgī suggests she traced her lineage back to the sage Garga, and Vācaknavī means “eloquent”, coming from the word “vāc”, or speech.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the Virtues of Cats</title>
      <link>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/virtuous-cats/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 22 Nov 2020 13:01:27 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/virtuous-cats/</guid>
      <description>Two days ago, Aslan the foster cat moved in. He&amp;rsquo;s a big ginger and white beast, and he was found on the streets of Sofia, Bulgaria. He&amp;rsquo;s settled in well, and is now lording it over all of us here in Slaveykov Square. So I thought that was a good opportunity to read John Gray&amp;rsquo;s brisk and breezy new book Feline Philosophy: Cats and the Meaning of Life.&#xA;It might seem odd that Gray — famous for his philosophical pessimism — has decided to lapse into whimsy and write about cats.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Guan Zhong the Reformer</title>
      <link>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/guan-zhong/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Nov 2020 11:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/guan-zhong/</guid>
      <description>Life Guan Zhong (720 – 645 BCE) is one of the earliest named Chinese philosophers. He became Chancellor in the state of Qi, and was the traditionally cited as the author of a book called the Guanzi (or &amp;lsquo;Master Guan&amp;rsquo;), a vast treatise on statecraft, economics, politics and philosophy.&#xA;However, the evidence is that early versions of the Guanzi probably date back only to the second century BCE, and the text as it has come down to us was complied in the first century BCE by a scholar called Liu Xiang.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Secret Teachings of Pythagoras</title>
      <link>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/pythagoras/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Nov 2020 09:24:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/pythagoras/</guid>
      <description>Life Pythagoras was born some time after 570 BCE on the island of Samos. Some accounts say he travelled widely during his early life, as far as Egypt, Babylonia and Persia, and this may have had an influence on his philosophical development. Other stories say that he visited both Thales and Anaximander in Miletus whilst in his twenties. All these stories may be true, but we know little about his early life for certain.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fire and Flow: the Philosophy of Heraclitus</title>
      <link>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/heraclitus/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Nov 2020 09:11:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/heraclitus/</guid>
      <description>Life Perhaps fittingly for a philosopher who saw change as fundamental to the universe, our knowledge about Heraclitus himself is similarly changeable and hard to pin down. At various times in history, he has been referred to as the &amp;lsquo;weeping philosopher&amp;rsquo; (due to his supposed pessimism), and &amp;lsquo;Heraclitus the Obscure.&amp;rsquo; And this obscurity is amplified by the fact that all we have left of Heraclitus&amp;rsquo;s philosophy are scattered fragments quoted by later writers.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ptahhotep and the Emeralds of Wisdom</title>
      <link>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/ptahhotep/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Nov 2020 10:39:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/ptahhotep/</guid>
      <description>Life Where does philosophy begin?&#xA;If you ask a Western philosopher, they might say &amp;lsquo;with Socrates.&amp;rsquo; If you ask a Chinese philosopher, they might say, &amp;lsquo;with Confucius.&amp;rsquo; And of course, the question &amp;lsquo;where does philosophy being&amp;rsquo; is a flawed one: the love of wisdom — this business of asking questions about life and existence — has no real beginning. Human beings have always found themselves wondering about the world of which they are a part, wrestling with the strange, baffling business of being alive.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Aspasia, the Philosopher Who Taught Socrates Rhetoric</title>
      <link>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/aspasia/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Nov 2020 12:10:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/aspasia/</guid>
      <description>Life Aspasia was born to a high-ranking family in the town of Miletus (where Thales was also born) around 470 BCE. Details of her early life are hazy, and many of the accounts we have are unreliable; but it is likely that some time around 450 BCE she moved to Athens, fleeing political unrest. In Athens, she was classified as a resident alien, and lacked the rights of a citizen.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Diotima Climbs the Ladder of Love</title>
      <link>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/diotima/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Nov 2020 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/diotima/</guid>
      <description>Life Our knowledge of Diotima is so sparse that many people have concluded that she was not an historical figure, but instead a literary invention. Diotima appears as a character in Plato’s Symposium, where Socrates refers to her as “a woman of Mantinea—a woman who was wise in many things.” And our knowledge of her doesn’t extend far beyond this.&#xA;Diotima’s name means “honoured by Zeus.” Her name suggests that she was a priestess, and according to Plato’s Symposium, she was also a philosopher and one of Socrates’s teachers.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cultivating Ritual with Confucius</title>
      <link>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/confucius/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Nov 2020 09:54:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/confucius/</guid>
      <description>Life The traditional dates for Confucius’s life are between 551 and 479 BCE. This makes him the contemporary of Greek philosophers like Heraclitus and Anaxagoras. He was born in the small state of Lu, now in present-day China. Confucius’s ancestors were high-ranking, but his father died when he was young, and Confucius was brought up in relative poverty.&#xA;In his early adulthood, Confucius served in various offices in the court of Lu.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Thales of Miletus on Appearance and Reality</title>
      <link>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/thales/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Oct 2020 11:57:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/thales/</guid>
      <description>Life Thales of Miletus was born some time around 624 BCE. His birthplace, Miletus, was an important trading port in the Greek world, now on the coast of Turkey. And if Thales is credited with being the first philosopher in Ancient Greece, it is no surprise that he lived in a busy trading town. As strangers met in Miletus, they no doubt argued about their different world views as they looked for common ground to communicate and trade.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Socrates, Philosophical Trouble-Maker</title>
      <link>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/socrates/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Oct 2020 09:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/socrates/</guid>
      <description>Life Socrates (c.470 BCE — 399 BCE) was born in Athens, the son of a stonemason and a midwife. It is likely he worked for a time in the family business as a stonemason himself. He also undertook military service during the Peloponnesian War — perhaps one of the few times he travelled far from Athens.&#xA;His philosophical education was informal. He studied with the philosopher Anaxagoras. And according to his disciple Plato, he was also influenced by two women philosophers: Aspasia of Miletus, with whom he studied the arts of oratory; and the priestess Diotima of Mantinea.</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
