<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Interviews on Looking for Wisdom</title>
    <link>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/tags/interviews/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Interviews on Looking for Wisdom</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 16 Dec 2022 10:15:57 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/tags/interviews/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Barbara Stok, on Comics and Cynics</title>
      <link>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/barbara-stok-hipparchia/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 16 Dec 2022 10:15:57 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/barbara-stok-hipparchia/</guid>
      <description>Looking for Wisdom Interview: Comics artist and writer Barbara Stok talks about dogs, Cynics, philosophers, and the art of living. Here at Looking for Wisdom, we’ve long been fascinated by the Cynic philosopher Hipparchia. So we were wildly excited when we stumbled across Dutch comic artist Barbara Stok’s sublime The Philosopher, the Dog and the Wedding.&#xA;The book is a beautiful and meticulously researched graphic novel that reimagines Hipparchia’s life, and explores what we might learn from it.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Andy West on Philosophy, Prison, Freedom and Shame</title>
      <link>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/andy-west/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Dec 2021 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/andy-west/</guid>
      <description>Introduction Andy West is Philosopher in Residence at HMP Pentonville, and the author of the frankly brilliant The Life Inside: A Memoir of Prison, Family and Philosophy, which is due out from Picador in February 2022.&#xA;Q: One of the reasons I’m interested in doing these interviews is I want to get a sense of what it means to do philosophy. So my first question is this: how did you get into philosophy?</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sophie Grace Chappell on Plato and the Moral Imagination</title>
      <link>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/sophie-grace-chappell/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Aug 2021 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/sophie-grace-chappell/</guid>
      <description>On Philosophy, Mountains and Finding Your Deepest Impulse Sophie Grace Chappell is a philosopher, a poet, a mountaineer and a trans woman. She was born in Lancashire in 1964, and educated at Bolton School and Magdalen College, Oxford. She has taught at Oxford, UEA, Manchester, and Dundee. Since 1998, she has lived in Dundee with her family.&#xA;Her last book is Knowing What To Do (OUP 2014), and her next book is Epiphanies (OUP 2022).</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Alexus McLeod on Maya Philosophy</title>
      <link>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/alexus-mcleod-maya-philosophy/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Mar 2021 11:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/alexus-mcleod-maya-philosophy/</guid>
      <description>Introduction Alexus McLeod is originally from Washington, DC, and now living in West Hartford, Connecticut. He teaches at the University of Connecticut and writes on a host of topics: Chinese and Mesoamerican Philosophy, mysticism, political history, the history of science (particularly astronomy and medicine), and several other things besides. For much of the past year, like many of us, he has been living the hermit life. Camped out in his home office, he has continued his work exploring the riches of the world&amp;rsquo;s philosophical traditions.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Anna Ezekiel on Günderrode, Identity and Doing Philosophy Differently</title>
      <link>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/anna-ezekiel-karoline-von-gunderrode/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Jan 2021 11:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/anna-ezekiel-karoline-von-gunderrode/</guid>
      <description>Introduction Welcome to the first ever Philosopher File interview! In this interview, I&amp;rsquo;m talking to Anna Ezekiel, a philosopher originally from Scotland and now based in Hong Kong. Since 2014, Anna has worked as an independent scholar, living with ME / Chronic Fatigue Syndrome. She has a particular interest in German women philosophers.&#xA;Anna&amp;rsquo;s hugely readable and enjoyable translation of Karoline von Günderrode&amp;rsquo;s Poetic Fragments was published by SUNY Press 2016, and she is currently working on a further book of translations by Günderrode called Philosophical Fragments.</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
