<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Series on Looking for Wisdom</title>
    <link>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/tags/series/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Series on Looking for Wisdom</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 13 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/tags/series/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>7 Ways of Reading Philosophy: #6 Reading for laughs</title>
      <link>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/7-ways-06-for-laughs/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/7-ways-06-for-laughs/</guid>
      <description>When we moved the Looking for Wisdom HQ up to Scotland a year ago, we packed away all our philosophy books into boxes. There were a lot of boxes. So on the outside, with a big fat marker pen, we wrote the words: “Philosophy Books (warning: extremely heavy).” As jokes go, it was a pretty feeble one. But it kept us entertained through the stresses of the move.&#xA;This idea that philosophy is inherently and necessarily heavy is one that has a broad currency.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>7 Ways of Reading Philosophy #5: Reading While Drunk</title>
      <link>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/7-ways-05-drunk/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Jun 2022 09:16:49 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/7-ways-05-drunk/</guid>
      <description>Philosophers Behaving Badly? The philosopher Simone de Beauvoir was a big fan of philosophising while drunk. Along with her sidekick Jean Paul Sartre, De Beauvoir partied hard, with the full commitment you might expect given her existentialist tendencies. In this, she was part of a long tradition of philosophers who drink. This tradition is so well established that the bar-room philosopher has become a stock figure in popular mythology: the drunken rambler who lists across the room and corners you for a conversation about how you can be certain that the tables and chairs in the bar really exist.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>7 Ways of Reading Philosophy : #4 Reading Out Loud</title>
      <link>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/7-ways-04-out-loud/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Mar 2022 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/7-ways-04-out-loud/</guid>
      <description>The Silent Reader There&amp;rsquo;s a story that Saint Augustine (354 – 430 CE) tells about his meeting with Ambrose, the bishop of Milan. When Augustine turned up in Milan, it was in search of a teacher of rhetoric. And Ambrose was considered one of the best.&#xA;At the time, Augustine&amp;rsquo;s philosophical and religious commitments were to the doctrines of Manichaeanism. He was unimpressed by Ambrose&amp;rsquo;s Catholic teachings, even while he was impressed by his new mentor&amp;rsquo;s kindness and rhetorical skill.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Future of Work (Work #7)</title>
      <link>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/work07-the-future/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Jun 2021 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/work07-the-future/</guid>
      <description>Welcome to the final piece in our season three series on the philosophy of work. Over the last couple of months, we&amp;rsquo;ve been putting work under the philosophical microscope, and exploring why it plays such an important part in our lives.&#xA;In this final article, we&amp;rsquo;re going to go back over the territory we have covered, to see if we can now throw more light on the complex roles played by work in human life.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Opposite of Work Part 2: Philosophy and Play (Work #6)</title>
      <link>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/work06-philosophy-and-play/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 07 Jun 2021 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/work06-philosophy-and-play/</guid>
      <description>In the last article in this series, we started exploring the opposite of work. If we want to understand the role that work has in human life, it is useful to think about all the things that we don&amp;rsquo;t consider to be work.&#xA;Often we understand what things are in terms of what they are not. And this is certainly the case with work. So, we define work in opposition to other things that we see as non-work—for example idleness, or play.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Opposite of Work? All About Idleness (Work #5)</title>
      <link>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/work05-all-about-idleness/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 31 May 2021 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/work05-all-about-idleness/</guid>
      <description>Over the last four articles in this series, we have been exploring divergent ideas of work. What is work? What role does it play in human life? How can we think better about work? Is work our salvation or our ruin? Is it the path that leads to virtue, or does it lead to our own destruction?&#xA;But when you start to think about work, you are also—by implication at least—thinking about non-work.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spiritual Damage: How Work is Bad for Us (Work #4)</title>
      <link>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/work04-spiritual-damage/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 May 2021 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/work04-spiritual-damage/</guid>
      <description>In last week&amp;rsquo;s piece, we explored how work might of benefit to us—how it might even be our salvation. For some thinkers, work is inherently ennobling and self-improving. It is, as Carlyle put it, a “purifying fire, wherein all poison is burnt up.”&#xA;Even if we don&amp;rsquo;t go as far as Carlyle, we have already seen that work can be beneficial in that it provides us with a range of both internal and external goods.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>7 Ways of Reading Philosophy: #3 Reading self-interestedly</title>
      <link>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/7-ways-03-self-interest/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 May 2021 10:48:44 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/7-ways-03-self-interest/</guid>
      <description>In the last article in this series on different approaches to reading philosophy, I talked about the rights of the reader to plot a course through whatever they are reading in whatever way they wish—doubling-back, skipping, haphazard and unsystematic, leaving books unfinished.&#xA;A reader who does this might seem, to their more sober peers, to be wilfully irresponsible, or failing in their duties as a reader. But in this article, I want to push the virtues of non-dutiful reading a little further, and I want to argue that one fruitful way of reading philosophy (and, for that matter, anything else) is to read out of self-interest.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Goodness of Work: Virtue, work, and salvation (Work #3)</title>
      <link>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/work03-virtue-salvation/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 May 2021 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/work03-virtue-salvation/</guid>
      <description>In this article, we&amp;rsquo;re going to explore the idea that there is something inherently good about work, that work may in some sense be our salvation.&#xA;Probably all of us grumble about our work from time to time. But for all our grumbling, we often see work in itself as a good thing. We praise people for working hard, and we criticise them for slacking off. We tell each other how hard we are working, and when we do, we feel the warm glow of virtue.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Life of Activity: Work, Labour and Action (Work #2)</title>
      <link>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/work02-the-life-of-activity/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 May 2021 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/work02-the-life-of-activity/</guid>
      <description>What is work? And how can we think better about work? Like many other things, we more or less know what work is when we don&amp;rsquo;t think about it too hard. But when we try to think a bit more deeply, or a bit more systematically, it becomes harder to figure out. So in this piece, we&amp;rsquo;ll be looking at the philosopher Hannah Arendt, whose exploration of the vita activa, or “the active life”, is a useful way to start getting a handle on the role that work plays in human life.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>&#34;Love and Understanding&#34;: The tangle of love and wisdom (Love #7)</title>
      <link>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/love07-love-and-understanding/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Apr 2021 13:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/love07-love-and-understanding/</guid>
      <description>The Love of Wisdom, and the Wisdom of Love Welcome to the final piece in our series on love. In this article, we&amp;rsquo;re going to be looking at the idea of philosophy as the love of wisdom. And we&amp;rsquo;re going to ask about whether there is a deeper connection between wisdom and love.&#xA;The first person to talk about philosophy as the love of wisdom was the Greek philosopher Pythagoras. The idea that philosophy is the love of wisdom—rather than, for example, the practice of wisdom—puts a bit of a distance between us and the wisdom that we aspire to.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>“Will You Still Love Me Tomorrow?” Love, trust and the future (Love #6)</title>
      <link>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/love06-will-you-still-love-me/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 05 Apr 2021 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/love06-will-you-still-love-me/</guid>
      <description>Introduction Imagine you&amp;rsquo;ve been dating somebody for a while. Things are going well. You like each other, and the dates are all enjoyable and fun. You are pretty happy with how things are progressing. But one day, the other person turns to you—an intense look on their face—and says in a tremulous voice, “I love you.”&#xA;You are stunned. Astonished. This puts things on a different footing. Everything has moved up a notch, and you are not sure how to respond.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Love Lifts Us Up Where We Belong? Love, transcendence and madness (Love #5)</title>
      <link>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/love05-love-lifts-us-up/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Mar 2021 11:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/love05-love-lifts-us-up/</guid>
      <description>Love, we are told, lifts us up where we belong: “Where the eagles cry / On a mountain high… / Far from the world we know / Where the clear winds blow.”&#xA;When we are in love, the world takes on a different, more giddying perspective. But shifts in perspective are tricky things. When we are loved-up and out of our right minds, are we at last seeing the world clearly?</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>7 Ways of Reading Philosophy: #2 Reading haphazardly</title>
      <link>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/7-ways-02-haphazardly/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 Mar 2021 07:34:58 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/7-ways-02-haphazardly/</guid>
      <description>Philosophers and storytellers The moment you pick up a philosophy book, if you are anything like me, you will almost immediately feel heavy with a cluster of obligations. The obligation to understand. The obligation to take this great work seriously. And the obligation to read systematically, one page at a time.&#xA;But as I suggested in the previous article in this series on reading philosophy at a gallop, this approach can slow you down—to the extent that you end up grinding to a halt.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>You Sexy Thing: Getting philosophical about sex (Love #4)</title>
      <link>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/love04-you-sexy-thing/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Mar 2021 11:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/love04-you-sexy-thing/</guid>
      <description>A complicated business&amp;hellip; Of all areas of human life, sex is one of the most complicated. It is the place where biology, culture, ideas of the good life and weighty moral claims collide. Questions about sex are one of the great human preoccupations. Questions like: How much sex should we have? Should we have as much as possible? Or—like the Buddhist monks, wary of desire—should we choose to abstain? Whom should we have sex with?</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>7 Ways of Reading Philosophy: #1 Reading Like Napoleon</title>
      <link>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/7-ways-01-napoleon/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Mar 2021 11:30:32 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/7-ways-01-napoleon/</guid>
      <description>When reading philosophy, the advice is often to read slowly and carefully, tortoise-style, making sure you understand every point before going on to the next. But in this article — the second in my ongoing series on how to read philosophy — I want to persuade you that this can sometimes be the very worst approach. And to do so, I&amp;rsquo;m going to take my lead from the German philosopher Franz Rosenzweig (1886-1929).</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Something So Right: Love and Justice (Love #3)</title>
      <link>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/love03-something-so-right/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Mar 2021 17:32:50 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/love03-something-so-right/</guid>
      <description>Taking your father to court The philosopher Socrates is outside the court in Athens. He has been accused of impiety and corrupting the minds of the youth of the city—a charge for which he will soon be executed. As he is idling in the street outside the courthouse, he comes across an earnest young man called Euthyphro. The young man is bringing a charge of murder against his father, something that is all but unthinkable in Athenian society.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>7 Ways of Reading Philosophy: An Introduction</title>
      <link>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/7-ways-introduction/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Mar 2021 11:40:51 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/7-ways-introduction/</guid>
      <description>Philosophy can often appear to be a daunting subject. All those great minds! All those long words! All those endless sentences that go on for half a page! The popular image of philosophy—an image that some philosophers are reluctant to dispel—is that it is an unusually difficult pursuit. And so perhaps it is not surprising that many readers sit down to read philosophy full of good intentions, only to find themselves grinding to a halt in a strange cocktail of frustration, inadequacy, and despair.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>We All Stand Together: Love, connection and community (Love #2)</title>
      <link>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/love02-we-all-stand-together/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Mar 2021 11:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/love02-we-all-stand-together/</guid>
      <description>Social primates Whatever else it might be about, love is about connection. It is about how we relate to each other. It is about how we feel about others, how we think about them, how we connect with them, what we do with them. Love is not so much personal as interpersonal.&#xA;So one way to make inroads into thinking about love is by thinking about what it means to be live alongside others.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Let&#39;s Do It: The Philosophy of Love (Love #1)</title>
      <link>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/love01-lets-do-it/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Mar 2021 11:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/love01-lets-do-it/</guid>
      <description>Welcome to our Season Two Looking for Wisdom Course Birds do it. Bees do it. And according to Cole Porter, even educated fleas do it (although I&amp;rsquo;m not quite so sure). But what is this thing called love? What does it mean to fall in love? And why does love loom so large in our individual and collective lives?&#xA;Welcome to season two in our Looking for Wisdom course series, where we&amp;rsquo;re going to be exploring the philosophy of love.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Giving up on Philosophy? The Science of Wisdom (Wisdom #7)</title>
      <link>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/wisdom07-the-science-of-wisdom/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Feb 2021 11:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/wisdom07-the-science-of-wisdom/</guid>
      <description>Welcome to the final piece in this short series on wisdom. Over this series, we&amp;rsquo;ve explored a rich range of traditions to try and get a handle on what wisdom is (if it is anything at all), how it matters (if it matters), and how to cultivate it (if it is the kind of thing you can cultivate).&#xA;We&amp;rsquo;ve covered a lot of ground over the past few articles. So in this piece, we&amp;rsquo;re going to take a quick tour of the territory we have explored.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Opposite of Wisdom: A Fool&#39;s Philosophy  (Wisdom #6)</title>
      <link>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/wisdom06-a-fools-philosophy/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Feb 2021 11:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/wisdom06-a-fools-philosophy/</guid>
      <description>If philosophy has always been preoccupied with wisdom, its relationship with the opposite of wisdom—foolishness—has always been a vexed one. One reason for this is that throughout the history of philosophy, the relationship between wisdom and foolishness has not been one of simple opposition. Instead, it seems that for some philosophers, at least, there is a kind of wisdom in foolishness.&#xA;We already know that Socrates was a self-confessed know-nothing. And also we know that for the Zhuangzi there is something wise in giving up in the pursuit of wisdom.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Nurturing the Sprouts of Wisdom (Wisdom #5)</title>
      <link>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/wisdom05-nurturing-the-sprouts/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Feb 2021 11:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/wisdom05-nurturing-the-sprouts/</guid>
      <description>Wisdom, virtue and the art of cultivation If wisdom is something desirable, something to which we can aspire, then how do we go about becoming wiser? We saw in the second piece on Aristotle that wisdom involves both thinking (theoria) and doing (praxis). A wise person is somebody who thinks about things clearly and who also acts well. They have both intellectual and practical virtues. And ideally, these virtues support each other.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>That Gut Feeling: Wisdom and the body (Wisdom #4)</title>
      <link>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/wisdom04-that-gut-feeling/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 25 Jan 2021 11:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/wisdom04-that-gut-feeling/</guid>
      <description>Going with the gut How do we know what is the wise thing to do? What makes for a wise action? In the heat of the moment, how do we decide? If you talk to some philosophers, they might tell you that we simply have to reason things out. But experience suggests that things don&amp;rsquo;t work like this. More often than not, we don&amp;rsquo;t have time to sit down and theorise our way to an answer.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Limits of Wisdom (Wisdom #3)</title>
      <link>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/wisdom03-the-limits-of-wisdom/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 Jan 2021 11:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/wisdom03-the-limits-of-wisdom/</guid>
      <description>Socrates and Zhuang Zhou on not knowing Welcome back. In the previous piece, we saw how Aristotle carves up human activity to distinguish between production, chosen action and contemplation. And we looked at the distinction between theoretical wisdom and what Aristotle calls phronesis or practical wisdom. According to Aristotle, we can develop our faculties to become wiser, both in terms of how we think about the world and in terms of how we act.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Navigating Wisdom with Aristotle (Wisdom #2)</title>
      <link>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/wisdom02-navigating-wisdom/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 Jan 2021 11:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/wisdom02-navigating-wisdom/</guid>
      <description>Wisdom, thinking and doing Welcome to the second piece in this series on wisdom: what it is and why it matters. In this piece, we&amp;rsquo;re going to be plunging into the work of Aristotle, one of Ancient Greece&amp;rsquo;s most profound thinkers, to ask about the relationship between wisdom, thinking and doing.&#xA;Wisdom, as we saw in the last essay, is more complex than it first seems. When we say someone is wise, we are not saying they possess just a single quality.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>What is Wisdom? (Wisdom #1)</title>
      <link>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/wisdom01-what-is-wisdom/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Jan 2021 11:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/wisdom01-what-is-wisdom/</guid>
      <description>Welcome This is the first in a seven-part series on wisdom. Over this series of articles, we&amp;rsquo;re going to be asking what wisdom is (if it is anything at all), how it matters (if it matters), and how to cultivate it (if it is the kind of thing you can cultivate).&#xA;In an everyday sense, we seem to have a pretty good grasp of what we mean when we talk about wisdom.</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
