<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Blogs on Looking for Wisdom</title>
    <link>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/tags/blogs/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Blogs on Looking for Wisdom</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 28 Jan 2024 00:16:46 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/tags/blogs/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Wansha Philosophy Salon</title>
      <link>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/wansha-philosophy-salon/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 28 Jan 2024 00:16:46 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/wansha-philosophy-salon/</guid>
      <description>My own philosophical education happened more or less by accident. In my twenties, I was a serious practitioner of Buddhism. I lived in a succession of Buddhist communities, working in temporary jobs, living on a shoestring, and spending my days writing and meditating. It was not financially sustainable in the long term, and the books I wrote at the time were all more or less unpublishable; but during these years of Buddhist practice, I had the luxury of having time to think.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Music is Joy</title>
      <link>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/music-joy/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Jan 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/music-joy/</guid>
      <description>On 21 January, we ran our first Wind&amp;amp;Bones public philosophy salon in Chinese, in collaboration with the Wansha Performing Arts Centre (涴莎藝術展演中心) in Tainan, Taiwan. We&amp;rsquo;re running these salons monthly, and we&amp;rsquo;re planning to publish an essay on the topic of the salon after each one. This is the first one, where we talked about philosophy and music.&#xA;A human universal Music is about as close to being a human universal as anything.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Looking for Wisdom in Taiwan</title>
      <link>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/in-taiwan/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 08 Sep 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/in-taiwan/</guid>
      <description>Here at Looking for Wisdom, 2023 has run away with us. No sooner had we set up the new site than we got involved in all kinds of other projects, and we had no choice but to put our work on the site temporarily to one side. Since we last posted, Hannah has had a short story collection accepted for publication and so is busy with endless edits, and Will has accepted a full-time job with Parami University in Myanmar, working online teaching philosophy and writing.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Combat, Play and Aesthetic Experience: Three Metaphors of Philosophy</title>
      <link>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/combat-play-and-aesthetic-experience/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 May 2022 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/combat-play-and-aesthetic-experience/</guid>
      <description>Two Men, Fighting You don&amp;rsquo;t notice it at first.&#xA;The two men are fighting it out with big sticks. One has blood streaming down his face. He lifts his arm to bring his cudgel down hard on his opponent&amp;rsquo;s head. The other man lifts his arm to protect himself, while reaching back to swing his own club from the side.&#xA;We don&amp;rsquo;t know why they are fighting, or over what. Maybe they are battling for something important.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Weaving the Net of Argument</title>
      <link>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/weaving-the-net/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Feb 2021 16:27:15 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/weaving-the-net/</guid>
      <description>Three radical women philosophers from the ancient world Although it is sometimes said that the history of philosophy is the history of human attempts to understand ourselves and the world, if you pick up any introductory philosophy textbook, it doesn&amp;rsquo;t take long to realise this isn&amp;rsquo;t quite true. Philosophy may claim to talk about human universals, but it&amp;rsquo;s hard to sustain this claim when most of the named figures in the historical traditions of the world are men: the history of philosophy is also the history of the exclusion of women&amp;rsquo;s voices from these conversations about what it means to be human.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the Virtues of Cats</title>
      <link>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/virtuous-cats/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 22 Nov 2020 13:01:27 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.lookingforwisdom.com/virtuous-cats/</guid>
      <description>Two days ago, Aslan the foster cat moved in. He&amp;rsquo;s a big ginger and white beast, and he was found on the streets of Sofia, Bulgaria. He&amp;rsquo;s settled in well, and is now lording it over all of us here in Slaveykov Square. So I thought that was a good opportunity to read John Gray&amp;rsquo;s brisk and breezy new book Feline Philosophy: Cats and the Meaning of Life.&#xA;It might seem odd that Gray — famous for his philosophical pessimism — has decided to lapse into whimsy and write about cats.</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
